Finding Aid for George D. Wilder Papers, 1904-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George D. Wilder Papers 1904-1971 1911-1942
Wilder, George D. (George Durand), b. 1869.
1 linear ft.
85486 Aa 2
Missionary to China, ca. 1900-1939. Letters, 1911-1932, to family members describing in detail missionary life, the political situation in China, and family matters; diary, 1942-1943, describing internment in Peking by the Japanese Army; letter of son, Theodore Stanley Wilder, to his grandmother concerning China experiences; reminiscences of T. S. Wilder, and photographs and other materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. Theodore S. Wilder (donor no. 5977 ).
The collection is open to research.
George Durand Wilder was born in Ripon, Wisconsin on June 26th, 1869, the son of Theodore Wilder and Frances Ellen (Durand) Wilder. George Durand Wilder attended Yankton Academy and College before enrolling in the Theological Seminary at Oberlin in 1891. He received his Bachelor's Degree of Divinity from Yale University in 1894.
In 1894, Wilder was ordained a Foreign Missionary in Oberlin, and he traveled to Tungcho China with his mother. Wilder began his evangelistic, as well as his educational work in Tientsin China. He later returned to Tungcho to be elected pastor of the native church. During the Boxer Rebellion (1900), Wilder assisted hundreds of Chinese Christian refugees as well U.S. soldiers in caring for the wounded, taking care of their laundry, and other manual needs.
In 1910, Wilder began teaching Theological Seminary at the University of Peking. He continued to teach in theological schools until his retirement in 1938. Wilder then served as the Secretary of North China Committee on Coordination of Emergency Relief in Tehsien, located in the Shatung Province. Due to escalating conflicts between Japan and China, Wilder was detained in Japan. He and his wife later returned to the United States in May of 1943.
George D. Wilder married Gertrude Stanley (OC 1894). Both worked as Missionaries in China. They had four children; all of whom studied at Oberlin College; Theodore (OC 1918), Margaret (OC 1921), Ursula (OC 1923), George Durand (1917-1920).
George Durand Wilder died on Sunday, May 5th, 1946.
_____________________________________
This biographical sketch excerpted from the Oberlin College Archives website
The collection consists of two series of papers. First there are letters that Wilder wrote to family members describing his life as a missionary in China. The next series of other papers includes a diary describing his internment by the Japanese during World War II and a remembrance of the life and work of his missionary parents written by Theodore S. Wilder.
Subjects:
China--History--1861-1912.; Missionaries--China.; Prisoners of war--China.; Prisoners of war--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons, Japanese.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China--Missions.; Hiking.; Missionaries--China.; Missions--China.; Wilder, George D. (George Durand), b. 1869.
Contributors:
Wilder, Theodore Stanley.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Letters to family
  - 1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912 (Box 1)
  - 1913 (Box 1)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916 (Box 1)
  - 1917 (Box 1)
  - 1918 (Box 1)
  - 1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921 (Box 1)
  - 1922 (Box 1)
  - 1923 (Box 1)
  - 1924 (Box 1)
  - 1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926 (Box 1)
  - 1927 (Box 1)
  - 1928 (Box 1)
  - 1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
  - 1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935 (Box 1)
  - 1936 (Box 1)
  - 1937 (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942 (Box 1)
  - Excerpts of letters selected by Cynthia Ritsher, 1911-1915 (Box 1)
- Other papers
  - Translation by G. D. Wilder of Chinese novel "Cat City" by Lao She, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Diary describing internment by the Japanese, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Impressions of China, ca. 1900-1912 by T. S. Wilder entitled "The China Years of George Durand and Gertrude Stanley Wilder" (Box 1)
  - Letters of Theodore and Durand Wilder to Grandmother and mother and family, 1910-1913 (Box 1)
  - Transcript of oral history interview conducted by Louise Hathaway Stanley (China Missionaries Oral History Project, University of California, Claremont), 1971 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook concerning International Monetary Commission to Honan, 1904 (Box 1)
    (include articles by G.D.W. entitled "The Peking-Hankow Overland Route")
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
Related Material
The library also houses the papers of the daughters of George and Gertrude Wilder. The Ursula Wilder Daniels collections includes letters received from her parents while they were stationed in China. The Margaret Wilder Menzi papers contains journals and other papers of her stay in China. Both the Oberlin College Archives and the Cornell University Library have small collections of George D. Wilder papers.